{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This event’s fourth principle declared that “superior orders” do not relieve a person from lawful\nresponsibility. Seven subjects of these events were taken to Spandau. Their location was chosen\nsymbolically, as it had hosted an annual propaganda rally and was the city where, in 1935, a harsh set of\nanti-Semitic laws was signed. Luftwaffe commander Hermann Goring was sentenced to death at, for ten\npoints, what series of trials in which Nazi leaders were tried for war crimes?",
      "answer": [
        "Nuremberg trials",
        "Nuremberg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this modern day country, Boleslaw [boll-eh-slav] the Pious of this country’s Piast Dynasty\ngranted Jews legal rights with the Statue of Kalisz [kal-eesh]. In this modern day country, the Szaltcha\n[SHALL-chah] enacted the Golden Liberty under its Jagiellion [yah-gell-ee-on] dynasty. This modern day\ncountry has been partitioned between Russia, Prussia, and Austria. For ten points, name this eastern\nEuropean nation with capital Warsaw.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s autobiography details his successful separation of the conjoined twins Josef and Theresia\nBinder, though his scientific credentials were criticized in 2015 after he denied Big Bang theory. This\nauthor of Gifted Hands gave the keynote address at the 2013 National Prayer Breakfast and, in September\n2015, stated that a Muslim should not be in charge of the United States. For ten points, name this\nRepublican presidential candidate and retired neurosurgeon.",
      "answer": [
        "Ben Carson",
        "Carson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person came to power after his wife ran over her father’s body with a chariot on the Vicus\nSceleratus. This person obtained the Sibylline Books from the Cumaean Sibyl. He allied with Lars Porsenna\nto try to regain power after Lucius Junius Brutus’s forces drove him out due to public indignation when\nhis son, Sextus, raped Lucretia. For ten points, name this successor to Servius Tullius, the last king of\nRome.",
      "answer": [
        "Tarquinius Superbus",
        "Tarquin the Proud"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This founder and editor of The Crisis magazine broke with an organization he co-founded over his\nopinion of the “separate but equal” doctrine. This man’s Niagara movement disagreed with Booker T.\nWashington’s Atlanta compromise, instead holding that the small, elite “Talented Tenth” should seek\nfull political authority in the South. For ten points, name this author of The Souls of Black Folk and\nco-founder of the NAACP.",
      "answer": [
        "William Edward Burghardt Du Bois",
        "W.E.B. Du Bois",
        "Du Bois"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler faced early trouble from two Eberhards, of Bavaria and Franconia, and his half-brother\nThankmar during his early reign. Liudolf, this man’s son, fought against him before a notable battle, and\nJohn XII crowned this man before being deposed by this ruler. This son of Henry the Fowler was aided by\nConrad the Red to defeat the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld. For ten points, name this Saxon German\nking, the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Otto I",
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A revival of this group that started at one its communities in Watervliet was called the Era of\nManifestations. This religious group uses a heart in a palm to symbolize its founder, Ann Lee’s, teachings.\nAaron Copland’s Appalachian Spring was influenced by this sect’s hymn Simple Gifts. This group broke\nwith the Quakers on lay celibacy. For ten points, name this religious group, nicknamed for its members’\ndancing during prayers.",
      "answer": [
        "Shakers",
        "United Society of Believers in Christ’s Second Appearing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Chicago’s Marina Towers provides 19 stories of this feature, which is often required in residential\nareas at a ratio of 1 unit per residence. These features may contribute to climate change by replacing\ngreen areas with paved asphalt. The Americans With Disabilities Act requires a certain percentage of\nthese places to be reserved for handicap-accessible use. For ten points, name this urban feature found\noutside stores and along curbs, where cars are left when not in use.",
      "answer": [
        "parking spaces",
        "parking lots"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician explained his views of federalism in his Disquisition on Government, and he described\nslavery as a “positive good.” He succeed Abel Upshur, who was killed in the USS Princeton explosion, as\nSecretary of State under John Tyler. For ten points, name this South Carolina politician who served as\nVice President for John Quincy Adams and Andrew Jackson who supported nullification.",
      "answer": [
        "John C. Calhoun",
        "Calhoun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This character discusses fighting off sea monsters called “nicoras.” Wiglaf is the only person who\nattends this man in death, and is crowned king as a result. Unferth apologizes for doubting this character\nby granting him the sword Hrunting. For ten points, name this title character of the oldest surviving work\nof Old English poetry, an epic hero defeats Grendel.",
      "answer": "Beowulf"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What man became France’s first Socialist president in 1981?",
      "answer": [
        "Francois Mitterand",
        "Mitterand"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s head was immersed in a jar of blood by Queen Tomyris to satisfy his bloodlust. This\nmonarch used camels to win the Battle of Thymbra, defeating Croesus of Lydia. His capture of Babylon\nis detailed in his namesake Cylinder, and Isaiah refers to him as a messiah for his freeing the Jews from\nthe Babylonian Captivity. The satrapy system was created by, for ten points, what first Achaemenid ruler\nof the Persian empire?",
        "answer": [
          "Cyrus the Great",
          "Cyrus II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aside from the Cylinder, most of what is known of Cyrus’ reign comes from what “father of\nhistory,” who traced the origins of the Greco-Persian War in his Histories?",
        "answer": "Herodotus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Suvorov invaded this country through the St. Gotthard Pass during the French\nRevolutionary wars. The Toggenburg War was fought by the Old Confederacy of this country, which\nwas formed from Uri, Schwyz, and Unterwalden. The Kappel wars were fought in this country, where\nNapoléon established the Helvetic Republic. Zürich is one of eight Old Cantons in, for ten points, what\nAlpine country that has its capital at Bern?",
        "answer": "Switzerland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author of Institutes of the Christian Religion and supporter of predestination fled to\nSwitzerland and eventually led the church of Geneva.",
        "answer": [
          "John Calvin",
          "Calvin"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This university hosted the 1942 Rose Bowl after large outdoor gatherings during wartime were banned\non the west coast. It won one national championship when Gordon Hayward’s half court shot barely\nmissed. The “air ball” taunt was popularized by fans of this university’s basketball team, who camp\noutside Cameron Indoor Stadium in a tent complex named for its head coach. For ten points, name this university in Durham, North Carolina, which has won five men’s\nbasketball titles under Mike Krzyzewski [sha-SHEF-ski].",
        "answer": [
          "Duke University",
          "Duke"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1992 NCAA Men’s Basketball championship game, Duke defeated this Big Ten state\nschool’s “Fab Five,” including Jalen Rose, who later claimed that Duke only recruited black players who\nwould be “Uncle Toms.”",
        "answer": [
          "University of Michigan",
          "Michigan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The largest city in this country is home to the Ipiranga Monument, where its founder proclaimed\nits independence in 1822. Oscar Niemeyer planned a new capital city for this country in 1956, to replace\na southern city on Guanabara Bay that hosted the 2016 Summer Olympics. For ten points, name this\nSouth American country, whose city of Sao Paulo is the largest in the Americas and whose capital was\nonce Rio de Janeiro.",
        "answer": "Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This planned city in central Brazil replaced Rio de Janeiro as capital in 1960.",
        "answer": "Brasilia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A piano suite by this man had six movements dedicated to friends killed in World War I. This\ncomposer of Le Tombeau de Couperin included a “Danse Generale” in the finale of his ballet Daphnis et\nChloe. He also wrote a piece which opens with a flute playing a melody that repeats in a long crescendo\nover a snare drum ostinato. For ten points, name this French composer of Bolero.",
        "answer": [
          "Maurice Ravel",
          "Ravel"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ravel wrote two of these pieces for soloist and orchestra, one of which, named “for the left\nhand,” was for Paul Wittgenstein, who had lost his right arm in World War I.",
        "answer": "piano concertos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man married his first cousin Zerelda Simms in the same year that his gang killed Pinkerton\nagent, Louis Lull. John Newman Edwards published this man’s letters in the Kansas City Times. Cashier\nJoseph Heywood was killed when this man, with his brother Frank, tried to raid the First National Bank\nof Northfield, Minnesota. For ten points, name this American outlaw of the Wild West who was killed for\nthe wanted money by Robert Ford.",
        "answer": [
          "Jesse James",
          "James"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jesse James led “Bushwhackers” for this short-lived nation that was constricted by Winfield\nScott’s Anaconda Plan.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate States of America",
          "CSA",
          "the Confederacy"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “Loyal Nine” fought the passage of this law, which led to riots led by Ebenezer Mackintosh.\nGeorge Grenville proposed this law, which led to the formation of Committees of Correspondence and the\nSons of Liberty and whose repeal was followed by the Declaratory Act. For ten points, name this 1765 law\nthat taxed documents in the American colonies.",
        "answer": [
          "Stamp Act",
          "Stamp"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man’s mansion was ransacked during protests from the Stamp Act. He later served as the\nRoyal Governor of Massachusetts and was replaced by Thomas Gage after the Boston Tea Party.",
        "answer": [
          "Thomas Hutchinson",
          "Hutchinson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was said to have employed and later killed Candagirika in an exquisite torture chamber\nknown as his Hell. He carved the wheel of dharma on a pillar at Sarnath, and this promulgator of the\nRock and Pillar edicts experienced a moment of remorse after the conquest of Kalinga. For ten points,\nname this third Mauryan emperor, known as the Great.",
        "answer": [
          "Asoka the Great",
          "Asoka"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the bloody Kalinga war, Asoka’s remorse led him to convert to this religion.",
        "answer": "Buddhism"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "CRASHES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Dow Jones average crashed in 1929, starting the Great Depression.",
          "answer": [
            "New York City",
            "New York",
            "NYC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Company whose Windows operating system shows a “blue screen of death” after it crashes.",
          "answer": "Microsoft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Award ceremony where Crash won Best Picture in 2004.",
          "answer": [
            "Academy Awards",
            "Oscars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American company whose 777 jet suffered its first fatal crash with Asiana Flight 214 in San Francisco.",
          "answer": "Boeing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Australian airline whose last fatal crash was in 1951.",
          "answer": "Qantas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea north of Sicily over which Itavia Flight 870 may have been shot down in 1980.",
          "answer": [
            "Tyrrhenian Sea",
            "Tyrrhenian"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity, such as the semper augustus whose Dutch speculative market crashed in 1637.",
          "answer": [
            "tulip bulbs",
            "tulip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First U.S. space station, which de-orbited in 1979 and crashed in Western Australia.",
          "answer": "Skylab"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE ROARING TWENTIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The color describing Tuesday, October 29th, 1929, when the stock market crashed?",
          "answer": "black"
        },
        {
          "question": "the tax-cutting U.S. President who succeeded Warren G. Harding?",
          "answer": [
            "Calvin Coolidge",
            "Coolidge"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The New York Yankee slugger who hit 60 home runs in 1927?",
          "answer": [
            "George Herman “Babe” Ruth",
            "Babe Ruth",
            "Ruth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The F. Scott Fitzgerald novel about a millionaire’s obsession of Daisy Buchanan?",
          "answer": "The Great Gatsby"
        },
        {
          "question": "The African-American cultural movement led by Claude McKay and Langston Hughes?",
          "answer": "Harlem Renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for women who broke social norms by bobbing their hair, smoking, and listening to jazz?",
          "answer": "flappers"
        },
        {
          "question": "The ornamental, yet industrial art movement that inspired New York’s Chrysler building?",
          "answer": "Art Deco"
        },
        {
          "question": "The whites-only New York City nightclub that housed Duke Ellington’s band?",
          "answer": "Cotton Club"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "During the 1920’s, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "AUSTRALIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The largest city, home to a famous opera house designed by Jorn Utzon?",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "The capital, grown by Sir Robert Menzies?",
          "answer": "Canberra"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city targeted by Japanese air strikes in World War II and named for the English author of The\nOrigin of Species?",
          "answer": [
            "Darwin",
            "Charles Darwin",
            "Port Darwin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the vast, arid region of largely unsettled inland Australia?",
          "answer": "Outback"
        },
        {
          "question": "The island state once known as Van Diemen’s Land?",
          "answer": "Tasmania"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest state and former site of the Swan River Colony?",
          "answer": "Western Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city that annually hosts the Australian Open of tennis and hosted the 1956 Summer Olympics?",
          "answer": "Melbourne"
        },
        {
          "question": "The bay where James Cook first landed the Endeavour in Australia?",
          "answer": [
            "Botany Bay",
            "Botany"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In Australia, what is..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man succeeded Nathaniel Lyon as the Commander of the Department of the West\nduring the Civil War. Fighting during the Mexican-American War was ended in one (20 pts) ",
        "territory after this man signed the Treaty of Cahuenga. His refusal to step down as the\nmilitary governor of California led to being court martialed by (10 pts) ",
        "Stephen Kearney. He finished\nsecond in the 1856 Presidential election to James Buchanan. For ten points, name this explorer who was\nthe first Republican presidential nominee."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John C. Fremont",
        "Fremont"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One work by this man shows a member of the White League shaking hands with the\nKKK above a shield that reads “Worse than Slavery.” Another (20 pts) ",
        "artwork by this man\nshows a man’s head replaced by a moneybag, and he depicted one institution as a tiger\nmauling a woman in a Roman Colosseum as faux-Emperor (10 pts) ",
        "Boss Tweed looks on. For ten\npoints, name this 19th century cartoonist for Harper’s Weekly who feuded with Tammany Hall."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Nast",
        "Nast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event ended the Peace of Saint-Germain-en-Laye. Pope Gregory XIII sent a Golden\nRose to Charles IX in commemoration of this event, which saw Charles Danowitz kill\nAdmiral (20 pts) ",
        "Gaspard de Coligny. It took place in the aftermath of the marriage between\nMargaret of Valois and (10 pts) ",
        "Henry III of Navarre and was instigated by either Henry of Guise or\nCatherine de Medici. For ten points, name this 1572 massacre of Huguenots."
      ],
      "answer": "St. Bartholowmew’s Day Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Dog Tax War was begun by members of this ethnic group. Europeans allying with\nthese people were known as “Pakeha.” Te Kooti founded a form of Christianity that likened\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "plight of these people to that of the Israelites; that religion is Ringatu. This group\nsuffered great losses as a result of the (10 pts) ",
        "Musket Wars. For ten points, name these people believed\nto have arrived in New Zealand from Polynesia in the 13th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Maori"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Upon this man’s release from Pendennis Castle, he was gifted supplies in Cork, though he\nwould not be free until was exchanged for the prisoner Archibald Campbell. He was captured\nby (20 pts) ",
        "Guy Carleton at the Battle of Longue-Pointe. William Delaplace surrendered to\nthis man before he captured (10 pts) ",
        "Saint-Jean and Crown Point, and he led a force founded at the\nCatamount Tavern. Benedict Arnold captured Fort Ticonderoga with, for ten points, what patriot who\nled the Green Mountain Boys in Vermont?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ethan Allen",
        "Allen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man broke up the Canal Ring as Governor of New York. The Senate appointment\nof Illinois’ David Davis led to this man (20 pts) ",
        "losing an election when, after voting along\nparty lines, a 15-member commission decided not to award this man any of the disputed (10 pts) ",
        "electoral college votes. For ten points, name this winner of the popular vote for the Presidency in 1876\nwho ultimately lost the election to Rutherford B. Hayes."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Samuel J. Tilden",
        "Tilden"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road named for this man was the target of Operation Barrel Roll. This man, who\ntried to oppose French colonialism in his home country at the Treaty of (20 pts) ",
        "Versailles, used\nSoviet and Chinese support to build an army capable of defeating the French at Dien (10 pts) ",
        "Bien Phu. He authorized the Tet Offensive, the turning point of a war that ended after this man’s death\nwith the fall of Saigon. For ten points, name this victorious North Vietnamese leader, now the namesake\nof Vietnam’s largest city."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ho Chi Minh",
        "Ho"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2015, Executives for this country’s flag-carrying airline were attacked after announcing nearly\n3,000 job cuts. In June, its CNIL threatened Google with fines if they did not apply the\nright to be forgotten to their global searches. During this country’s elections for the (20 pts) ",
        "European Parliament, the right-wing National Front seized 25% of the vote, while its\ndomestic government was led by (10 pts) ",
        "Socialist Prime Minister Manuel Valls. For ten points, name this\nEuropean country whose President in 2015, also a Socialist, was Francois Hollande."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Right before the end of this conflict, action in the Battle of 73 Easting continued\nat Norfolk, and Frederick Franks lost almost no troops while demolishing the (20 pts) ",
        "Republican Guard in this war. It began over disputes about the Rumaila oil field.\nChuck Horner commanded troops in this war before the arrival of (10 pts) ",
        "Norman\nSchwarzkopf. For ten points, name this war in which Operation Desert Storm reacted to Saddam\nHussein’s invasion of Kuwait."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Persian Gulf War",
        "Gulf War",
        "First Gulf War",
        "First Iraq War"
      ]
    }
  ]
}